There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
How can we improve the capacity of
our blood vessels to repair themselves?
Here’s our first story.
The capacity of our blood
vessels to repair themselves
is dependent on
endothelial progenitor cells
that emerge from stem cells
in our bone marrow
to patch up any holes
in our endothelium,
the innermost lining
of our blood vessels
that keeps our blood
flowing smoothly.
Lower levels of circulating
endothelial progenitor cells
in the blood correlates
with arterial diseases
like erectile dysfunction.
Higher numbers,
on the other hand,
are correlated with
a significantly reduced risk
of death
from cardiovascular causes.
Before we explore
how to boost our levels,
let us first establish
cause-and-effect.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
was performed in men and women
with peripheral
vascular disease,
a circulation disorder
characterized by the narrowing
of blood vessels outside
of the heart or brain.
The arteries supplying
blood to their legs
were so ravaged by disease
that they could only
walk about a minute
before the muscles in their legs
cried out in pain
from lack of oxygen.
For each study participant,
one leg was randomly selected
to be injected with cells
from their own bone marrow
and the other was injected
with their own peripheral blood
as a control.
Not only was pain-free walking
time significantly extended
in the marrow-injected leg,
they were less likely
to subsequently lose it.
Severe limb ischemia,
lack of oxygen,
from peripheral
vascular disease
carries a 10 to 40 percent
amputation rate
within six months.
In the control group,
14 percent were forced
to undergo a major amputation
compared to zero
in the bone marrow group.
Given these remarkable benefits,
the link between higher numbers
of endothelial progenitor cells
and lower risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease
may indeed by causal.
Short of sticking a large bore
needle into your hip,
how else can we
cultivate and release
more endothelial progenitor
cells into our system?
Smoking cessation is one of the
most important and effective
lifestyle changes to increase
the number and function
of active endothelial
progenitor cells.
Cutting down isn't enough.
There are 20 cigarettes
in a pack.
If you only smoke
about one a day,
wouldn't you think you'd only
have one-twentieth the risk
of cardiovascular disease,
compared to smoking
the whole pack?
Based on a meta-analysis
of more than a hundred studies,
smoking only about
one cigarette a day
caused around 10 times the risk
of cardiovascular disease
you'd expect by that logic,
compared to smoking
a pack a day.
There is no
safe level of smoking
when it comes to heart attack
and stroke risk.
Even exposure to second-hand
smoke can deteriorate
our circulating endothelial
progenitor cell count,
so even just being
around smokers is risky.
Randomized controlled trials
show exercise training
can actually boost endothelial
progenitor cell circulation.
In a study of middle-aged
and older sedentary men,
for example, three months
of moderate aerobic exercise--
mostly walking,
with some participants
starting to jog a bit
as their fitness improved--
led to a doubling of
endothelial progenitor cells
in their bloodstream.
Regular aerobic exercise
could be considered
a "first line" strategy
for helping to prevent and treat
arterial aging.
What about diet?
A randomized controlled trial
showed that reducing
saturated fat,
mostly in the form of butter,
significantly elevated
endothelial progenitor
cell numbers,
consistent with a study
on baboons showing that
even a few weeks
of a high-cholesterol,
high-fat diet
could cause dramatic
premature epithelial
cell senescence.
Individual foods that
have been shown to increase
circulating endothelial
progenitor cells
include berries,
onions, and green tea,
and a diet centered completely
around whole plant foods
not only showed a boost
in endothelial progenitors,
but an improvement
in endothelial function,
along with a drop
in LDL cholesterol.
In our next story,
we look at how vegetables
such as beets and arugula
can improve athletic performance by
improving oxygen delivery and utilization.
It's great that we can improve athletic
performance eating a few beets,
but so what if you run 5% faster?
It can be a fun experiment
to eat a can of beets
and maybe shave a
minute off your 5k time.
But these are the people
who could really benefit
from a more efficient use of oxygen:
those suffering from emphysema.
Yeah, young healthy adults
eating greens and beets
can swim, run, and cycle
faster and farther,
but what about those who get out
of breath just walking up the stairs?
Do nitrate-rich vegetables
work where it counts?
Yes, significantly extended time
on the treadmill after
two shots of beet juice.
It's great that beet
juice can decrease
blood pressures in
young healthy adults,
but what about in those who really
need it, older overweight subjects?
Just one shot of beet juice a day
versus berry juice as a control,
and in a few weeks a significant
drop in blood pressure.
But within just a few
days after stopping
after three weeks
of beeting themselves up,
blood pressures went back up.
So we have to eat our vegetables
and keep eating our vegetables.
Why did it take until
2015 to publish a study
on lowering blood pressure in
people with high blood pressure?
You'd think that'd be
the first group to try it on.
Who's going to fund it,
though — Big Beet?
Blood pressure medications rake in
more than $10 billion dollars a year.
You can't make billions on beets.
But that's why we have charities
like the British Heart Foundation,
which funded a study to give
folks with high blood pressure
a cup of beet juice
a day for four weeks.
After all, high blood pressure
may be the #1 risk factor
for premature death in the world.
In ten years it could affect nearly
one in three adults on this planet.
But put them on beet juice
and blood pressures dropped
and kept dropping until it
was stopped after a month.
With so many people with high blood
pressure even despite treatment,
an additional strategy, based on the
intake of nitrate-rich vegetables,
may prove to be both
cost-effective, affordable,
and favorable for a public health
approach to hypertension.
What about those with
peripheral artery disease?
Tens of millions with atherosclerotic
clogs impairing blood flow to their legs,
which can cause a cramping pain
in the calves called claudication
due to lack of blood flow
through the blocked arteries,
severely limiting one's ability
to even just walk around,
but just drink some beet
juice and walk 18% longer.
They measured the actual oxygenation
of their blood within their calf muscle.
The nitric oxide from vegetable nitrates
not only improves oxygen efficiency
but oxygen delivery by
vasodilating blood vessels,
opening up arteries so
there's more blood flow.
I’m surprised beet
juice companies
aren’t trying to position
themselves as veggie Viagra.
It could certainly explain why
those eating more veggies
have such improved
sexual function,
though this study was
a snapshot in time,
so you can't tell which came first.
However, it seems more reasonable
that low fruit and vegetable consumption
contributes to erectile dysfunction,
rather than the other way around.
What about the most
important organ, the brain?
Poor cerebral perfusion – lack of
blood flow and oxygen in the brain –
is associated with cognitive
decline and dementia,
and they showed that
the nitrate in vegetables
may be beneficial in treating
age-related cognitive decline.
They showed a direct
effect of dietary nitrate
on cerebral blood flow
within the frontal lobes,
the areas particularly
compromised by aging.
This is a critical brain area for
so-called executive function,
basic task and problem solving,
important for day-to-day functioning.
The nitrite from nitrate
has been shown
to not just increase blood
flow to certain areas of the body,
but also acts preferentially
in low oxygen conditions,
allowing it to increase blood flow
precisely in the areas where
it's needed the most.
And that's what they
found in the brain:
increased blood flow to the
at-risk areas of the aging brain.
And the only side effect
of beeting your brains out?
A little extra color in your life.
Do legumes—beans, chickpeas,
split peas, and lentils—
work only to prevent disease,
or can they help treat
and reverse it as well?
Here are some answers.
Legumes, by which they mean all kinds of
beans, chickpeas, split peas, and lentils,
are an excellent source of many essential
nutrients—vitamins, minerals, fibers,
antioxidants, and not
just an excellent source,
perhaps the single cheapest source.
In terms of nutrition density per penny,
the four that really pull off
from the pack are pinto beans,
lentils, black beans, and kidney beans.
And, all that nutritional quality
may have beneficial effects on
excess body weight, insulin resistance,
high cholesterol, inflammation,
and oxidative stress—
all major cardiovascular risk factors.
So, do men and women who eat more
beans tend to have less heart disease?
Yes, suggesting that increasing
legume intake may be an important part
of a dietary approach to the primary
prevention of coronary heart disease
in the general population,
meaning prevention of heart disease
in the first place.
But, maybe those eating more
bean burritos are just eating
less beef burritos?
They took that into account,
controlling for meat intake,
fruits, and vegetables
and smoking and exercise,
and still, the bean eaters
appeared to be protected.
Note the highest category
here was eating
legumes 4 or more times a week.
In my Daily Dozen, I recommend people
eat legumes three times—a day!
In Costa Rica, they were able to find
enough people eating beans every day,
and so, even after controlling for
many of the same things,
like intake of saturated
fat and cholesterol,
one bean serving a day was
associated with a 38% reduction
in the risk of heart attack.
Yeah, but do you actually
get to live longer too?
Yes, apparently so, an 8%
lower all-cause mortality,
again after adjusting for
other dietary factors.
You can’t control for everything, though.
You can’t really prove cause
and effect until you…
put it to the test.
Randomized controlled
interventional trials
have found that dietary bean intake
does significantly reduce
bad cholesterol levels,
dating back a half century to 1962.
Measure cholesterol levels at baseline,
and then add beans to their diet,
and then remove beans from their diet.
And, look, beans have
a low glycemic index
and saturated fat content,
and are high in fiber,
potassium, and plant protein,
each of which independently confers
blood pressure-lowering effects.
But, whether there’s sufficient evidence
to emphasize beans alone
to lower BP is unclear.
Therefore, what we need is a
systematic review and meta-analysis
of controlled feeding trials and...
here it is.
And, what they found is that beans
do indeed lower blood pressure
no matter where you start out.
OK. So, beans may be able
to prevent artery disease,
but what about reversing it?
Can the daily consumption of beans—
other than soy,
reverse vascular impairment
due to peripheral artery disease?
Peripheral artery disease results
from a decrease in blood flow
to the legs due to a buildup
of atherosclerotic plaque higher up.
Yeah, soybeans may help,
but what about other beans?
So, they had twenty-six individuals
with peripheral artery disease
consume one serving a day
of a combination of beans,
split peas, lentils, and
chickpeas for 8 weeks.
Basically, how you diagnose
and follow-up the disease
is with the ankle-brachial index,
which is just the ratio of
blood pressure at your ankle
compared to your arm.
Once it dips below point nine,
that means you must have some kind
of clogs in blood flow
to your lower body,
but eat some beans,
and you may get a significant increase,
enough to push four of 26 participants
up into the normal range
after just 8 weeks, eating some beans!
Now, there was no control group,
but people tend to get
worse, not better.
The researchers conclude
a legume-rich diet can elicit major
improvements in arterial function.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.